Burr School Records
Connecticut Historical Society
Burr School records
1907-1952,1965
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Burr School (Hartford, Conn.)
2.5 linear feet (5 boxes)
Historical Note
The school, located at 400 Wethersfield Avenue, was built in 1915 and included a gymnasium and swimming pool. In 2005 the building underwent extensive renovations.
Scope and Content
This collection of materials was found in a closet at the Alfred E. Burr School and was rescued from disposal by an electrician. The documents are organized into four series.
Series I: Attendance records Attendance records were kept by classroom and are arranged chronologically in Series I. There are multiple volumes for some years.
Series II: State and City curriculum and teaching guides State Education and Hartford School Departments issued curriculum guides and conducted studies to improve teaching. Their published reports are organized chronologically in Series II. Among the more interesting publications are several Works Progress Administration reports, Hartford school surveys, community adjustment programs in postwar America, a bibliography of inter-racial understanding, and a booklet entitled “What About Communism?” Some of the resources that follow the curriculum guides were published by organizations outside of Hartford but provide insight into what topics were taught, and how they were taught. A sample was made of the more than 500 student passbooks; every 20th booklet was retained.
Series III: Financial records Financial records are incomplete but the bills and bank statements, 1935-1942, illustrate the types of supplies needed in various classes and how those materials were purchased from local vendors. An index to supplies needed at the school, 1965, is the most recent document found in Series III.
Series IV: M. Delott Garber teaching files M. Delott Garber was principal of the Alfred E. Burr School in the 1940s and he also taught education courses at the University of Connecticut. Reports submitted by students from one of his university classes in 1949 complete the collection and are arranged in Series IV.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Contents:
- Series I. Attendance records
  - Volume 1-31. Attendance records, 1907-1930
- Series II.State and city curriculum and teaching guides
  - Homemaking and industrial arts, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Survey of Hartford Public Schools, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Surveys of Hartford schools, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hartford Occupational Briefs (WPA); curriculum for High School English, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bibliography of visual education, publications of the University of Connecticut Curriculum Laboratory, inventory of the Hartford Public Schools Film Library, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Curriculum report, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Curriculum report, 1940-41 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - World history curriculum, evaluation of teaching in secondary school, school health policies, science curriculum, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Examinations, community adjustment programs in the postwar period, bibliography of inter-racial understanding, reading lists, 1942 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Instructional practice, homemaking curriculum, guide to study of civics, 1945 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Science and civics curricula, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - English in 7th grade, school personnel certification, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Home economics and city government curricula, Teacher Education Quarterly, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hartford schools handbook, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Study in music, grades kindergarten to sixth, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Civics teaching guides, including “The Negro History Bulletin”, America Goes to the Polls, and the Bill of Rights (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Economics teaching guides, including “What About Communism?” and brochures on labor (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - English teaching guides and resources (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Health teaching guides and resources (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General subject resources (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sheet music for chorus, ca. 1928 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Student passbooks, 1927-1928 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
- Series III.Financial records
  - Bills, bank statements, 1935-1942 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Cashbook and journal, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Supply list, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series IV. M. Delott Garber teaching files
  - Research reports submitted for a class at the University of Connecticut Graduate School of Education, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)